<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" ><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="4.0.0">Jekyll</generator><link href="/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" /><link href="/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" /><updated>2020-08-30T13:34:38+02:00</updated><id>/feed.xml</id><title type="html">DecentNet</title><subtitle>Decentralized, privacy, open-source, cool technologies, networks, software you should use.</subtitle><entry><title type="html">Bitmessage review</title><link href="/blog/20200830-bitmessage.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Bitmessage review" /><published>2020-08-30T02:20:00+02:00</published><updated>2020-08-30T02:20:00+02:00</updated><id>/blog/bitmessage</id><content type="html" xml:base="/blog/20200830-bitmessage.html">&lt;p&gt;I love the internet. Not what the internet has become today. I love the internet where you can be anonym, you can say anything, you don’t have to be afraid of SJWs or governments muting you or doxxing you.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Decentralization is the way for an internet like that. &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/Bitmessage/PyBitmessage&quot;&gt;Bitmessage&lt;/a&gt; is a tool to achieve it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Bitmessage is one of the only few tools that isn’t controlled by anyone, that isn’t censored by anyone. It’s serverless. Everyone has a copy of every message, no one can say what you’re doing on Bitmessage. It works with Tor, so you can even hide that you’re using Bitmessage. It’s fully text-based. POW works to stop spammers. You can have as many identities as you want, it’s fully anonym. You can safely, effortlessly leave your contact information anywhere, and anyone can reach you anytime. It’s open source.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It doesn’t matter if PyBitmessage development is slow, or if at some point it stops. Bitmessage is a free protocol, anyone can continue the development or even develop new and better clients.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Decentralized e-mail is a powerful tool that everyone and every website should use.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Chans are great. They are like e-mail mailing lists. It’s a fully uncensored forum that’s built into Bitmessage.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I don’t care if conspiracy theories or filth gets posted. If they couldn’t be posted, the program (the internet) couldn’t be truly free. It’s not the task of ISPs, governments, corporations or developers to censor what I can see and post. I’m a grown-up, I can filter out the messages myself.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Another similar project is &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/i2p/i2p.i2p-bote&quot;&gt;I2P-Bote&lt;/a&gt;. Someone recently picked it up again. I hope to try it out some time.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;BM-2cUCQxqh6PyT5jcoKwuZkikQh3RXKjv9Q5&lt;br /&gt;
4A792049C8DD2B40DA125FE9D6E8C27AC1E025FB&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html">I love the internet. Not what the internet has become today. I love the internet where you can be anonym, you can say anything, you don’t have to be afraid of SJWs or governments muting you or doxxing you.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Download torrents anonymously through I2P for free</title><link href="/blog/20200329-download-torrents-through-i2p.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Download torrents anonymously through I2P for free" /><published>2020-03-29T01:20:00+01:00</published><updated>2020-03-29T01:20:00+01:00</updated><id>/blog/torrent-on-i2p</id><content type="html" xml:base="/blog/20200329-download-torrents-through-i2p.html">&lt;p&gt;When you torrent on clearnet, your IP is visible to other peers. Malicious actors might act as peers to de-anonymize you. Some people use VPNs to remain anonymous, but they cost money, and you can’t be sure how trustworthy your VPN provider is. &lt;a href=&quot;https://geti2p.net/&quot;&gt;I2P&lt;/a&gt; is a free anonymity network that works well with file transfers, that’s a good alternative to VPNs.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;(Disclaimer: You should only download legal content. Use this article at your own risk. This article doesn’t encourage illegal behaviour. You are responsible for everything you do.)&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I2P is still in beta, it might have bugs, so be careful with it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://geti2p.net/en/download&quot;&gt;Download&lt;/a&gt; and install I2P. On Windows, if you have trouble starting I2P, try installing it as a service.&lt;/p&gt;

    &lt;p&gt;You’ll probably want the Java version, because it comes with a built-in BitTorrent client. You can use &lt;a href=&quot;https://i2pd.website/&quot;&gt;I2PD&lt;/a&gt; too, but you’ll have to set up your torrent client yourself. For the Java version you’ll have to &lt;a href=&quot;https://openjdk.java.net/&quot;&gt;install Java&lt;/a&gt; too.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Install the &lt;a href=&quot;https://geti2p.net/firefox&quot;&gt;browser bundle&lt;/a&gt;, or make a fresh &lt;a href=&quot;https://support.mozilla.org/en-US/kb/profile-manager-create-remove-switch-firefox-profiles#w_start-the-profile-manager-when-firefox-is-closed&quot;&gt;profile in Firefox&lt;/a&gt; for I2P, where you install NoScript, HTTPS Everywhere and maybe some other privacy add-ons. &lt;a href=&quot;https://geti2p.net/en/about/browser-config#firefox&quot;&gt;Configure Firefox&lt;/a&gt; to use 127.0.0.1:4444 as proxy. You should disable JavaScript (in NoScript or in your Firefox settings).&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;You can control I2P through &lt;a href=&quot;http://127.0.0.1:7657&quot;&gt;127.0.0.1:7657&lt;/a&gt;, the I2P Router Console. It takes a few minutes for I2P to start up. You’ll want to &lt;a href=&quot;http://127.0.0.1:7657/config&quot;&gt;set the bandwidth&lt;/a&gt; used by I2P to something close to your internet bandwidth. In your physical router and your software firewall you should port-forward the ports used by your I2P installation; you can check the ports in your &lt;a href=&quot;http://127.0.0.1:7657/confignet&quot;&gt;Network Configuration&lt;/a&gt;. If you can’t reach some eepsites, you should add some &lt;a href=&quot;http://127.0.0.1:7657/help#addressbooksubs&quot;&gt;additional subscriptions&lt;/a&gt; to your Addressbook.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;I2P has a torrent client that automatically, securely routes your traffic through the I2P network. You can reach &lt;a href=&quot;http://127.0.0.1:7657/i2psnark/&quot;&gt;I2PSnark&lt;/a&gt; with the Torrents button in your router console. Under &lt;a href=&quot;http://127.0.0.1:7657/i2psnark/configure&quot;&gt;Configuration&lt;/a&gt; you can set where you want to download your files, and if you want to autostart your torrents when I2P starts.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Torrents hosted on clearnet trackers (usually) don’t work inside I2P. You can only connect to peers who also run I2P. You can find some trackers at the bottom of I2PSnark’s &lt;a href=&quot;http://127.0.0.1:7657/i2psnark/configure&quot;&gt;configuration page&lt;/a&gt;. Or you can search somewhere else. The I2P community is pretty active on Irc2P, the IRC network inside I2P; download &lt;a href=&quot;https://hexchat.github.io/&quot;&gt;HexChat&lt;/a&gt;, review the settings, remove any information about you or your computer, and join 127.0.0.1:6668.&lt;/p&gt;

    &lt;p&gt;Postman’s tracker is probably the most popular; you can search for torrents, or you can sort by swarm size to find popular ones.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;If you found something you want to download, copy its magnet link into I2PSnark. It’ll start connecting with other peers, start downloading and uploading pieces. Be patient, it’ll take some minutes for the torrents to start.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I2P is pretty slow, not many people use it yet, and you might not find some files you want on I2P trackers. But it’s the future of free anonymous file sharing. The more people who use it, the better it becomes.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html">When you torrent on clearnet, your IP is visible to other peers. Malicious actors might act as peers to de-anonymize you. Some people use VPNs to remain anonymous, but they cost money, and you can’t be sure how trustworthy your VPN provider is. I2P is a free anonymity network that works well with file transfers, that’s a good alternative to VPNs.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Website design, hosting</title><link href="/blog/20200308-website-design-experience.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Website design, hosting" /><published>2020-03-08T01:20:00+01:00</published><updated>2020-03-08T01:20:00+01:00</updated><id>/blog/website-experience</id><content type="html" xml:base="/blog/20200308-website-design-experience.html">&lt;p&gt;The website is static. This way I can host it on &lt;a href=&quot;https://pages.github.com/&quot;&gt;GitHub Pages&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;https://dat.foundation/&quot;&gt;Dat&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;https://ipfs.io/&quot;&gt;IPFS&lt;/a&gt; or some other cheap hosting provider. It’s really fast, it doesn’t require PHP or databases, it’s safe.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;GitHub Pages is free, convenient, reliable. Dat and IPFS are awesome technologies, it’s really cool that supporters of the website can pin it, potentially hosting it forever. And the users who might use Dat and IPFS to access the website will be the ones who are interested in the subject of the website, decentralized technologies. The &lt;a href=&quot;/about.html&quot;&gt;about page&lt;/a&gt; contains all the links where the website is accessible.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It is built with &lt;a href=&quot;https://jekyllrb.com/&quot;&gt;Jekyll&lt;/a&gt; with the &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/jekyll/minima&quot;&gt;Minima&lt;/a&gt; theme with some modifications. Free themes in Jekyll give you a pretty website design out of the box. They work well with smartphones, they are optimized for search engines. Jekyll has plugins for further features and customization. Jekyll gives a quick structure for your website, so you can start writing your pages right away, and it also has blogging capabilities.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The website doesn’t use JavaScript. Visitors can be sure it doesn’t run any malicious code, it doesn’t steal their data. It’d easily work on Tor or I2P where JavaScript is usually disabled. Blogs, Wikis, text and picture websites have no reason to run JavaScript, or at least always should work without JavaScript. Jekyll actually inserts some SEO tags with JavaScript by default, and I haven’t found an easy way to disable it yet, but I just delete those to keep the website pure.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The website is tiny. There are no images (at least not yet). Version 1 was about 70 KB. This makes it really easy for those who want to pin the website on Dat and IPFS. It also keeps the design clean, and hosting free/cheap.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The main page of the website is the most important, it hosts the list of technologies divided into categories. &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.privacytools.io/&quot;&gt;PrivacyTools&lt;/a&gt; was an inspiration, that’s the go-to place for most people to find privacy-oriented services. I chose the most important and awesome decentralized techs to review, and gave a few additional services a mention. This is my list, it’s about what I think is important, but I don’t know the whole spectrum of decentralized technologies equally well, so I welcome suggestions. I plan on updating the list over time. I’m trying to support these technologies by giving them visibility, and trying to create a place people can go to to discover tech they want to use. Most of these projects are really important, the free internet can’t exist without them anymore. You can’t stay anonym without anonymity networks. Traditional social media websites are centralized, heavily censored and harvest data from their users. Traditional messaging applications leak data to advertisers and law enforcement. Decentralized alternatives are crucial.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The blog is the secondary part of the website. Here I write posts that are connected to the technologies on the main page, guides on how to use them, further thoughts. Users of decentralized technologies might find these blog-posts useful.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;proofs&quot;&gt;Proofs&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The &lt;a href=&quot;../about.html&quot;&gt;about page&lt;/a&gt; has my PGP public key. I signed version 0.9 of the website markdown files to prove they were made by me. I timestamped the signed files with &lt;a href=&quot;https://originstamp.org/&quot;&gt;OriginStamp&lt;/a&gt; on the Bitcoin blockchain to prove the ownership of the website content. The &lt;a href=&quot;../proofs.html&quot;&gt;proofs page&lt;/a&gt; has all the instructions to verify these. Only accept cryptocurrency addresses and sensitive information from me if it has been signed with my PGP key.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;hosting-experience&quot;&gt;Hosting experience&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Hosting on GitHub Pages was really easy. I just created and set up an account, and pushed the built website with git.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Dat was fairly easy too. The &lt;a href=&quot;https://beakerbrowser.com/&quot;&gt;Beaker Browser&lt;/a&gt; has great, noob-friendly tools and instructions to share your files. After I started seeding the website files on my public key, I registered with a &lt;a href=&quot;https://hashbase.io/&quot;&gt;free pinning service&lt;/a&gt; that pulled the files from me with no problem.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;IPFS was harder. Jekyll uses absolute links, but IPFS URLs consist of the address of localhost or a clearnet gateway, the words “ipns” or “ipfs”, and the IPNS or IPFS hash of the website; so the absolute links don’t work. I haven’t found a way to use relative links yet, but I just manually edit the HTML of my pages.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Adding files and IPNS names from IPFS Desktop didn’t work for me, so I used the command line. Pinning was harder too. Some pinning services gave me errors, so I had to do some debugging. A lot of pinning services don’t support IPNS pinning yet, so I’ll have to manually update the IPFS hashes every time I update the website. Some pinning services work through an API, so it’s not that hard, and I heard some services support IPNS too.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Update 20200329: IPNS doesn’t seem to work when I’m not online, and I don’t have a domain, so I stopped pushing to IPFS. The absolute links might be a problem with Dat gateways too (but people probably use Hashbase or Beaker Browser with Dat, not gateways).&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html">The website is static. This way I can host it on GitHub Pages, Dat, IPFS or some other cheap hosting provider. It’s really fast, it doesn’t require PHP or databases, it’s safe.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Quick how to: Host a website on Dat (Beaker Browser) for free</title><link href="/blog/20200308-host-a-website-on-dat.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Quick how to: Host a website on Dat (Beaker Browser) for free" /><published>2020-03-08T01:10:00+01:00</published><updated>2020-03-08T01:10:00+01:00</updated><id>/blog/host-a-website-on-dat</id><content type="html" xml:base="/blog/20200308-host-a-website-on-dat.html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://dat.foundation/&quot;&gt;Dat&lt;/a&gt; is a peer-to-peer protocol. &lt;a href=&quot;https://beakerbrowser.com/&quot;&gt;Beaker Browser&lt;/a&gt; is a browser to browse websites hosted on it. If you visit a website, you download it from other peers, and you seed it further. If you want to support a website, you can pin it, so it’s always available on your computer for others to access (&lt;a href=&quot;dat://46415d000a5080de26f2458c4170e954c0e0ae0a914143aac09ab138b298019c/&quot;&gt;pin me!&lt;/a&gt;).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You can host your websites on Dat for free. There are no servers; users and pinning services can serve your files. There are free services that can make your website available on the clearnet.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You host only static websites on Dat. There are no servers to interact with, to host databases on. Static websites can still be used for a lot. With JavaScript you can access other peer-to-peer networks, and store data on if needed, like &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.iota.org/&quot;&gt;IOTA&lt;/a&gt; or &lt;a href=&quot;https://ipfs.io/&quot;&gt;IPFS&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Popular static site generators are &lt;a href=&quot;https://jekyllrb.com/&quot;&gt;Jekyll&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&quot;https://gohugo.io/&quot;&gt;Hugo&lt;/a&gt;, but there are many others. With these tools you can quickly, easily make a website or a blog that looks good, works well with phones and search engines. You don’t have to do any coding. You should keep your website small, so it’s easier to pin; compress your images.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/results?search_query=jekyll+tutorial&quot;&gt;Make a static website&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://beakerbrowser.com/install/&quot;&gt;Download Beaker Browser&lt;/a&gt;, set it up to your liking&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Menu &amp;gt; Create new &amp;gt; From folder &amp;gt; select the folder your website’s in&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Under Settings fill in the metaadata: Title, Description etc.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Under Files review the changes and Publish all&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Click Share and share your public key with your friends&lt;/p&gt;

    &lt;p&gt;The websites are identified by private keys (dat://46415d000a5080de26f2458c4170e954c0e0ae0a914143aac09ab138b298019c/ for example). While you’re online everyone can download your websites from you. You should use a pinning service to host your files even when you are offline. &lt;a href=&quot;hashbase.io&quot;&gt;HashBase&lt;/a&gt; is a popular pinning service that can host 100 MB for free. It gives you a subdomain, so it’s easier for you to share your website, and it makes your website accessible from the clearnet as well.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://hashbase.io/register&quot;&gt;Register on HashBase&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://hashbase.io/new-archive&quot;&gt;Upload archive&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Paste in your public key&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Give a name (subdomain) to your website&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You’re done. Your website is accessible from the clearnet under https://yourname.hashbase.io. It’s always available for everyone to visit. Share your website.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you’re on Dat, but you host your website on the clearnet in some other way too, like &lt;a href=&quot;https://pages.github.com/&quot;&gt;GitHub Pages&lt;/a&gt;, you should add a .well-known/dat and a  _config.yml file &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/pfrazee/pfrazee.github.io/commit/6e59d2eb4bcb10b9baf73a3de7d221e80d8190d8&quot;&gt;like such&lt;/a&gt;, so if people use the Beaker Browser (or a browser add-on), they are redirected to the decentralized Dat website.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Do you have a hobby you want to write about? Do you want a personal website, or a website for your small business? You can create a pretty, small, static website for free in some minutes or hours.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html">Dat is a peer-to-peer protocol. Beaker Browser is a browser to browse websites hosted on it. If you visit a website, you download it from other peers, and you seed it further. If you want to support a website, you can pin it, so it’s always available on your computer for others to access (pin me!).</summary></entry></feed>